In this lecture, we're going to explore the multi-core era with parallel processors.
We'll take a look at how trends in transistor scaling have motivated the shift towards parallel multi-core processors.
Then we'll talk about the concept of parallelism and dive specifically into hardware multithreading.
For years, computer architects have benefited from very favorable transistor scaling, or denard scaling,
named after Robert Denard, who published the observation.
The scaling trend was that as we make transistors smaller by a factor of x squared,
their voltage, capacitance, and switching delay all scale down by a factor of x.
So what did this mean for our processors and integrated circuits?
The dynamic power consumption of a processor is proportional to the number of transistors on the chip,
multiplied by the capacitance and voltage squared, multiplied by the activity factor,
which is how often the transistors switch for a given application, and finally multiplied by the processor frequency.
Now with transistor scaling, by a factor of x, we're able to fit x squared more transistors on chip
due to the x squared reduction in area per transistor.
At the same time, the energy cost per transistor goes down by x cubed,
while the processor frequency can go up by a factor of x due to the lower switching delay.
Together, all of these imply that if we're able to shrink the size of our transistors in the next generation of processors,
we're able to retain roughly the same total dynamic power as the previous generation,
while improving performance via the higher clock frequency and additional transistor logic.
This was a huge motivation for the processor industry.
As observed by Gordon Moore in 1965, now known as Moore's Law,
the processor industry was able to continually push for smaller transistors,
and thanks to cost-effective innovations in processed technology,
we were seeing the number of transistors roughly double every 18 months, as shown in this figure.
What this meant was that the new processors were able to greatly improve upon the performance of their predecessors,
thanks to a combination of more transistors per chip and higher operating frequencies.
All one needed to do was to buy next-year CPU and their existing software would get faster.
However, this was only part of the story.
These scaling trends held for a while since dynamic power dominated the power that leaked out of transistors,
even when they're not switching. This is known as static or leakage power.
As transistor voltages scaled down, the threshold voltages were slowly following suit,
leading to static power becoming more and more significant to the point that in recent years,
it can often dominate the dynamic power of the system.
Thus, the favorable scaling of voltage, capacitance, and delay were quickly diminishing due to leakage.
So with this, as well as practical thermal limitations, we hit the end of denart scaling around 2005.
Clock speed and power advancements drastically slowed.
But Moore's law continued to persist. We were able to build smaller and smaller transistors,
even if their power density wasn't improving.
So then how do we make good use of abundant transistors without being able to run our cores at higher frequencies?
The solution was parallel processing. By using our transistors for more independent processor cores,
we're able to get significant speed-ups by leveraging parallelism in our programs
without relying on continuous improvements in clock frequency.
To modify a quote from Yoda in Star Wars, begun, the multi-core era has.
Now before we get into the design of multi-core processors, we'll first discuss the concept of parallelism.
There are two broad classes of parallelism.
Compute-level parallelism is when multiple computation streams are executed simultaneously,
while data-level parallelism is when multiple data streams are processed simultaneously.
For now, we'll focus more on compute-level parallelism, particularly in the context of executing multiple threads.
It's important to use precise terminology and to note the difference between concurrency and parallelism.
Note that you may encounter varying definitions in literature,
but the common definition and what we'll assume for the purposes of this course
is the concurrency refers to the coexistence of multiple tasks in progress,
while parallelism is the physical execution of multiple tasks in a simultaneous manner.
You can think of concurrency as logically doing multiple things at once,
while parallelism is actually doing multiple things at once.
Concurrency is typically defined with a software system and algorithm,
while parallelism is defined by the hardware architecture.
An example of execution that is concurrent but not parallel
is context switching between multiple programs or threads in a single processor.
They never physically execute at the same time, but logically, they are concurrent.
I encourage you to come up with examples of execution that is parallel but not concurrent.
As a theoretical analysis, how can we compute the potential speedup of a program due to parallelism?
Say we have three processor cores in our system that are able to execute
arbitrary parts of your program in parallel.
Well, first we need to figure out how much of our program can actually be executed in parallel.
Naturally, this won't be the entire program.
There will likely always be some code that can't be parallelized.
So then given we execute the parallel code on the three processor cores,
we expect to get a 3x speedup of just the parallel portion of our program.
This will allow us to revisit Amdahl's law and see that it is quick and easy
to estimate how much program speedup you can get, given some number of cores.
Even with how simple Amdahl's law is, it's still able to shed some valuable insights.
Consider a program where 75% of its original execution time was spent on parallelizable code.
If we had infinitely many cores, our ideal speedup for the program would be 4x,
which is the case where all of our time is spent just executing the 25% sequential code
and the parallelizable code executes somehow in zero time.
Now you'd think maybe we can get pretty close to the ideal of 4x speedup with just, say, 4 cores.
But at 4 cores, we're just barely making over 2x speedup.
In fact, it takes quite a lot of cores to get asymptotically closer to the ideal, as shown here.
It turns out that even with nearly 100% of our program being parallel,
even a small percentage of sequential work, in this case 2% of our program,
can still greatly limit our achievable speedup.
Even with 100 cores in this case, we're still below the ideal speedup that we'd hoped to get.
Now in terms of implementing parallel processors,
Flynn's taxonomy is a useful guide for categorizing the fundamental approaches
based on compute-level parallelism and data-level parallelism.
SIMD, which is Single Instruction Multiple Data,
refers to processors that are able to perform a single instruction uniformly on a batch of data in parallel.
Examples of this include Cray Research's vector processors,
x86 for ARM vector instructions, and GPUs, which we'll get to in a later lecture.
MISD, or Multiple Instruction Single Data,
refers to processors that are able to perform multiple instructions in parallel that operate on a single piece of data.
This is less common, but is growing in interest recently.
So we'll be covering SIMD and MISD in a later lecture.
For now, we'll focus on MIMD, Multiple Instruction Multiple Data.
This is effectively running multiple threads, processes, programs
that are each running their own set of instructions and processing their own set of data.
Before we get into MIMD, it's important to draw the distinction between instruction-level parallelism and thread-level parallelism.
Instruction-level parallelism is when we can execute multiple instructions with a single thread of a program.
As we've already learned, this form of parallelism can be implemented via superscalar processors
that can execute multiple instructions in the same cycle.
On the other hand, thread-level parallelism is being able to execute multiple independent threads in parallel.
The key difference is that threads are well-defined with a software programmer,
whereas instruction-level parallelism is inferred by the absence of dependencies.
For this reason, thread-level parallelism tends to be more coarse-grained than instruction-level,
executing large chunks of code in parallel as opposed to per instruction basis.
To write multi-threaded programs, programmers will usually use APIs and libraries like POSIX threads or P-threads
to explicitly declare the creation and management of threads, as shown in this very simple example,
where the main thread creates an independent thread to run in parallel and call the printf function.
MIMD processors primarily exploit thread-level parallelism.
This was originally motivated by time-sharing, or context-switching, on a single processor,
as was implemented by most operating systems to support concurrent execution.
So because programs were already being written in a way to explicitly declare their parallel threads,
it became easy to build new processors that had multiple processing cores in them.
This made it very scalable for companies to build processors for different product lines and price levels,
having low-performance, low-cost, single-core options, versus high-performance, high-cost, multi-core options,
all being built off the same IP blocks and hardware.
Applications and operating systems were still able to run seamlessly on these systems
because the parallel processing was abstracted away from software.
This resulted in clear performance gains thanks to the additional throughput provided by parallel execution.
The granularity of MIMD processing can vary.
Within a single processor core, parallel execution can be supported
by implementing multiple hardware threads in the microarchitecture.
This is known as simultaneous multithreading SMT, or hyperthreading, in Intel's line of processors.
Chip multiprocessors, or CMPs, integrates multiple distinct processor cores that can execute one or more threads each.
Since these cores are no longer sharing hardware structures like the reorder, buffer, and register file,
any sharing or transfer of data between them must now go through the memory hierarchy
and what on-chip interconnect is used between them.
And finally, at a large scale, CMPs can be composed into clusters of processors connected via internet-working protocols,
as is done in modern data centers and warehouse-scale computers.
This visually recalls how we're able to extract instruction-level parallelism from a single thread or program.
With an in-order scalar core like our five-stage pipeline, we're only able to execute one instruction at a time.
Using a three-wide pipeline, we can build an in-order super scalar machine that can process multiple instructions at the same time,
just as long as they're independent and come one after another in program order.
Finally, with additional hardware complexity, we can allow instructions to bypass each other out of order
and fill up available pipeline slots to maximize performance.
Multi-threading is where we have two applications, or threads, running in the same processor system.
The simplest case is to execute the threads concurrently, but not in parallel, where the threads are time-sharing the hardware resources.
Simultaneous multi-threading is when the threads run on the same processor core but are able to partition or pool
the hardware resources so that they can coexist in the processor pipeline,
while a chip multiprocessor simply dedicates separate processor cores for the two threads.
The key trade-off here is that towards the right, the implementations become more complex but enable more opportunity for parallel speed-out.
An analogy to these forms of multi-threading is how groups of cars decide to travel to common destination.
Context switching is like convoying, where all cars in a group cluster together,
likely clogging up the entire road and potentially leaving some of its lanes, like the left turn lane, underutilized.
SMT is like allowing the cars to self-navigate to their common destination.
They all still share the road, but this improves the utilization of all lanes while coming at more complexity,
since each individual car is now treated as an independent entity.
Finally, for max throughput, we can allocate completely separate roads for the different groups of cars, like a CMT,
allowing them the freedom to reach their final destination without having to worry about getting in each other's way.
Simultaneous multi-threading can be implemented by taking an out-of-order superscaler processor
and allowing it to fetch from multiple different thread contexts in parallel.
Since the out-of-order execution engine already tracks all the necessary dependencies among instructions,
it can already support parallel execution of threads naturally, with only small changes in hardware.
To enable this, the in-order structures of the pipeline should be partitioned, such as the reorder buffer and map table.
This is to ensure that one thread stalling does not cause another independent thread to stall.
This is also necessary to make sure that we don't confuse the registers of one thread for another.
Since the two threads are compiled using the same ISA, they may use the same set of architectural register names, like T0 or S1,
but the threads are actually referring to their own versions of T0 and S1.
On the other hand, the out-of-order components can be pooled, like the reservation stations and functional units.
Even the physical registers can be pooled since the map table is partitioned
and will correctly distinguish registers owned by thread 1 from those owned by thread 2.
This illustrates that concept in more detail.
Thread 1 and 2 would have to have their own map tables, since their architectural registers are the same.
But the set of physical registers can be pooled and shared among them without harming correctness.
You can think of this as analogous to dealing with homonyms in virtual memory.
This shows an example of SMT in practice as implemented by Intel Hyperthreading,
where in-order structures like the decode queues and the reorder buffer are partitioned,
while the out-of-order engine can be almost entirely pooled, including the cache.
For even more parallelism, we can build a chip multiprocessor
by simply composing multiple uniprocessors together, each with their own microarchitecture and caches.
Often these cores will be connected together on the same cache and memory hierarchy,
allowing them to share the same physical memory.
We'll focus on building shared memory CMPs in the coming lecture.
Let's wrap up with a brief exercise.
Here's a program that you're planning to run on some parallel processor.
If this were a 5-core processor, and you know that 75% of your program's sequential runtime is parallelizable,
what would be the total program speedup?
We've discussed a law for this, so pause the video and please work through it.
This is simply revisiting Amdahl's law in the concept of parallel execution.
The 75% portion of your program can be sped up by a factor of 5 since you have 5 available cores.
The remaining 25% take the same amount of time,
so in total, your program ends up being 2.5 times faster when running on this parallel processor.